This is Otto Warbeer. He's a 21-year-old
American college student.
>> My crime is very severe and pre-planned.
I regret my actions more than anything.
>> 2 months ago, he went on a New Year's
party tour with a travel agency. The
destination was Pyongyang, the capital
of North Korea. On the early morning of
January 1st, 2016, I committed my crime
aimed at harming the work ethic and the
motivation of the Korean people. After a
night of partying, he allegedly took a
poster from the hallway of his hotel.
Shortly after, he was detained for
perpetrating a hostile act against the
Democratic People's Republic of Korea.
>> I understand the severity of my crime.
Now he's here trying to save his life at
the mercy of a totalitarian
dictatorship.
>> I have been very impressed by the Korean
government's humanitarian treatment of
severe criminals like myself and of
their very fair and square legal
procedures in the DPR Korea.
>> A communist regime that nurtures a deep
hate for America. The United States
administration already knows about my
act through the CIA and connived at my
crime.
>> Soon, the case of this college kid will
escalate the already tense relationship
between two nuclear powers.
>> North Korea best not make any more
threats to the United States.
They will be met with fire and fury.
Otto Warmbeer at this point has no idea
what he is about to face.
>> An American is being held captive in
North Korea. He was sentenced to 21
years of hard labor.
>> Those prisons are rough places. If
something very bad happened to him,
>> Americans fateful trip to North Korea.
>> Complete failure to recognize
fundamental human rights.
>> The dreams of a young man destroyed by
dubious charges from a ruthless regime.
>> This very press conference might be his
last chance to save his life.
I am the oldest son in my family. My
mother needs me. My father needs me. My
younger brother and my younger sister
need me. I entirely beg you, people
government of the DPR Korea
for your forgiveness.
Please, I have made the worst mistake of
my life. Otto Warmir won't survive and
his case will bring the US and North
Korea to the brink of war, but the
version of events many people remember
might not be true.
>> Confirmed.
>> Much of our research is based on this
extensive GQ article. Find the link in
the description.
New Year's Eve 2015. This is Kim IlSung
Square in Pyongyang. Thousands of North
Koreans have gathered to watch the
fireworks and greet the new year.
Among them is a group of tourists. These
are people from Europe, Canada,
Australia, and the US. They're here with
a travel agency, and they booked a
5-day, 4night, [music] New Year's party
tour for $1,200.
Otto Warbeer is one of them. Now, after
the fireworks, they returned to their
hotel, a 47story tower located on a
small island in the Taong River. It
boasts five restaurants, a bar, a sauna,
a massage parlor, even a bowling alley.
One of the restaurants revolves. Because
of its location, people call it the
Alcatraz of fun. During the tour,
they'll drink at a fancy bar and eat at
fine restaurants. And on [music] top,
they get the full propaganda tour.
They've already visited the 70-foot
bronze statues of Kim IlSung and Kim
Jong-, the country's first two
dictators. They're regarded as near holy
figures.
State propaganda has it that when Kim
Jong- was born at the sight of a holy
mountain, a double rainbow and a glowing
new star appeared in the sky. Today, his
birthday, the day of the shining star,
is a public holiday. Citizens
spontaneously salute the massive
statues, but it's impossible to say
whether it's real reverence or mandatory
homage.
Propaganda is everywhere. Billboards
show images of missiles striking the US
capital. Other posters sport slogans
like, "Let's arm ourselves strongly with
Kim Jong-'s patriotism."
Disrespecting the Communist Dynasty can
get you in big trouble. According to GQ,
the database center for North Korean
Human Rights confirmed a case of a
factory janitor being prosecuted for
bumping such a picture off the wall so
that it fell and broke. Otto and the
other tour members need to be careful.
One wrong move and they could face harsh
punishment.
Otto
was raised in a suburb outside
Cincinnati, Ohio. The oldest of three
siblings. In high school, he was
popular, athletic, and smart. At both
prom and homecoming, he was crowned
king. Speaking at his high school
graduation, he quoted Andy Bernard from
The Office.
>> I wish there was a way to know that
you're in the good old days before
you've actually left them.
>> Now he's majoring in finance. Halfway
through his junior year, he decides to
do a winter break adventure to North
Korea. It makes sense. He'll be studying
abroad in Hong Kong in the spring. In
2015, the State Department's travel
advisory for North Korea is clear. It
recommends against Americans traveling
there at all. On the other hand, the
website of Young Pioneer Tours, Otto
Wararmbe's travel agency, said that
traveling to North Korea was quote
extremely safe. The tour operator
specializes in taking you to
destinations your mother would rather
you stay away from. His parents had
their concerns, but as Cindy Warbeer
later said, why would you say no to a
kid like this?
Early in the tour, the group is visiting
this ship, the USS PBLO. The North
Korean military captured it in 1968. The
North Koreans claimed it had entered
their territorial waters. Now, it's a
tourist attraction. When the North
Korean tour guide explains that the ship
was seized from the United States, he
doesn't say the United States, he says
the Imperial Enemy.
Between 1950 and 1953, the US dropped an
estimated 635,000
tons of bombs on the country,
plus some 32,000 tons of Napal.
Major cities were obliterated. 75% of
Pyongyang was destroyed. During the war,
as many as a million civilians perished.
In 1953, a ceasefire ended combat in the
Korean War. But a peace agreement was
never signed.
Technically, the North is still at war
with the South and with its ally, the
US. Most Americans are unaware of this
war. So much so that the Korean War is
often referred to as the Forgotten War.
Not so in North Korea.
The North Korean tour guide explains
what happened back then to the 82
American sailors that were captured
along with the ship. They were beaten,
starved, and only released after 11
months.
Otto Warbeer is not visiting just any
country. He's in enemy territory.
Danny Graten, his roommate during the
tour, will later recount that Otto
seemed a little bit shocked. To lighten
the mood, he and the other tour members
give Otto a nickname, Imperial Enemy.
The rest of the tour goes smoothly.
sightseeing during the day, restaurants
and bars at night.
They even engage with the local kids by
having a friendly snowball fight.
One of the reasons people travel is to
understand the world a little better.
Brilliant does that for learning. It
helps you engage with ideas in a
hands-on way so you can unlock the
intuition you already have. Concepts
that once felt slippery start to click
and once they do, you begin to see
patterns everywhere. Instead of just
watching explanations, you're actively
working through problems, testing ideas,
and building real knowledge. We
particularly like Brilliant's
probability and chance course. It helps
you reason through uncertainty from
expected value to conditional
probability and makes you more confident
in the decisions you make. If leveling
up your math, data, or computer science
skills is on your list this year,
Brilliance courses adapt to you. They
start at the right level with
personalized practice you can actually
use so you hit the learning goals that
matter to you. To get started, go to
brilliant.org/fern
or scan the QR code. Brilliant is
offering 20% off an annual premium
subscription, giving you unlimited
access to everything on the platform.
Back to January 1st after the fireworks.
When the tour group returns to the Young
GTO hotel, they split up. Some go to the
bar. Danny Graten heads to the bowling
alley. They lose track of Otto.
When Danny gets to his room around 4:30
a.m., Otto is in bed, sound asleep.
Then, a day and a half later, the group
is ready to get on the plane. It's time
to go home.
As the last members of the group, Dany's
and Otto's passports are checked.
The officers take an unusually long time
to scan their documents.
Then Otto feels a sudden tap on his
shoulder. There are two North Korean
soldiers behind him. [music] They lead
him away.
Danny doesn't think much of it and
jokes, "Well, that's the last we'll ever
see of you."
2 and 1/2 months later, Otto is standing
trial in North Korea's Supreme Court.
He's accused of violating article 60 of
the DPRK criminal code, state
subversion. The central piece of
evidence is this CCTV footage.
It's timestamped. The early hours of New
Year's Day 2016. It shows a staffonly
area in the Yangakto Hotel. A shadowy
figure removes a poster from the wall
and appears to set it on the ground.
The poster looked like this, a
propaganda poster, and it contained the
Supreme Leader's name. Let's arm
ourselves strongly with Kim Jong-'s
patriotism. To remove it from the wall,
is a serious crime. A bid to impair the
unity of North Korea's people. And that
shadowy figure, according to the
prosecutors, that is Otto Wormbbeer.
The trial only lasts an hour. The Young
Pioneers North Korean tour guide
testifies against Otto. A second witness
takes the stand, an employee who says
they noticed the poster had been taken
from the wall. Otto's belongings are
presented as evidence and fingerprints
are shown on a flat screen TV. But most
of the supposed evidence came from
Otto's confession 2 weeks earlier. Here
he goes into the details. On January
1st, 2016,
New Year's Day, I committed severe
crimes against both the people and the
government of the DPR Korea. [music] The
task was given by the Friendship United
Methodist Church.
At the encouragement of the Z Society
and the connance of the United States
administration,
I came to commit this crime task. The
full story goes like this. His friend's
mother, a deaconess at the Friendship
Methodist Church in his hometown of
Cincinnati, Ohio, instructed him to deal
a blow to North Korea by stealing an
important political slogan to be hung in
her church as a trophy. As a reward,
he'd receive a used car worth $10,000.
Were he to be detained, the church would
pay his family $200,000.
The aim of this crime was to harm the
work ethic and motivation of the Korean
people.
>> He told his mother about his plans.
>> She cried and said not to do anything
dangerous.
I considered less, not wanting to hurt
my mother. But since then, I received
several alluring pressures from the
Friendship United Methodist Church,
leading me to finally decide on my crime
attempt. He then shared his plans with a
member of the Ziz Society, a secret
society at the University of Virginia
that Otto wanted to join. He'd heard all
of its members go on to get highpaying
jobs. He promised if I was successful,
he would help me gain membership in the
Z Society.
>> Finally, he decided to do it. After I
planned in detail to accomplish my plan,
I arrived in Pyongyang on December 29th,
2015 through Beijing. On the early
morning of January 1st, 2016,
I committed my crime of taking out the
important political slogan from the
staffonly area of the Angakto
International Hotel aimed at harming the
work ethic and the motivation of the
Korean people. And he explains the plot
goes all the way to the top. The United
States administration already knows
about my act through the CIA, which is
closely linked to the Z Society and
connived at my crime. The church, too,
is linked to the government.
>> The Friendship United Methodist Church
is not a typical church. It is very
wealthy with $42 million.
That is why the United States
administration has very close ties with
this church.
>> He was manipulated. Plain and simple.
>> I was clearly given the task by the
Friendship United Methodist Church. I
was encouraged by the Z Society. My
crime is very severe and pre-planned. I
regret my actions more than anything. I
beg for forgiveness and I beg for help
in any way possible to save my life.
Experts agree that Otto Warbeer's
confession seemed quite obviously
coerced and staged. North Korea has a
history of chorusing confessions and the
US accused North Korea of broadcasting
this one for propaganda purposes. A
member of the Ziz Society said Otto had
never approached them and denied any
affiliation with the CIA and the senior
pastor at Friendship United Methodist
Church said he didn't know of the
deaconess mentioned by Otto. But this is
later after it's too late. Now standing
before the Supreme Court, all Otto can
do is beg.
>> I was used and manipulated.
[snorts]
>> Please
stay with me.
Please save my life.
>> But his pleas fall on deaf ears.
He's handcuffed and led from the room.
He's been sentenced to 15 years of hard
labor.
2 days later on March 18, the Korean
Central News Agency released the CCTV
footage to the public. Western news
outlets treat the footage with
suspicion. That figure could be anyone.
One story notes that the corridor is
well lit, something that in a country
where electricity is scarce is far from
the norm for staff-only spaces. Some of
his tour mates give interviews. One of
them, Sarah McLaclin, says there was an
issue with the time shown in the video.
>> Your group had been out at a New Year's
Eve party in the hours before that. Were
you even back at the hotel then?
>> No, the time didn't match up at all.
>> According to her, the Young Pioneers
didn't return to the hotel until around
3:00 a.m., more than an hour after the
footage was allegedly captured. Another
tourm mate says in an interview with the
BBC that Otto was careful to observe the
rules. They'd been told not to take
pictures of military staff or
installations and he'd been nervous when
taking a photo with military personnel
in the background.
His
[music]
roommate Danny Graten also doubts that
it was Otto.
>> We never mentioned anything remotely
like that. He'd already but we'd already
bought some souvenirs. In my heart of
hearts, the guy I knew for three or 4
days was not that type of guy.
>> Everything about the whole story was
fabricated in my opinion. [music]
Otto's parents, Fred and Cindy, turned
to the Obama administration for help,
but the Warbeers later said they were
advised to keep quiet. According to GQ,
Robert King, the special envoy for North
Korean human rights issues, warned that
drawing media attention to the ordeal
might anger the regime. What makes it
even more complicated is that the United
States has never had a formal diplomatic
relationship with North Korea. There is
no US embassy in Pyongyang. The Swedish
ambassador serves as the liaison for
Americans, but the Swedes calls and
emails are met with silence.
The days turn to weeks turn to months.
Efforts at back channel diplomacy are
stymied. The issue is passed from one
administration to the next. No one knows
where Otto is, what he's doing, or how
he's being treated.
Then in early June 2017, some 17 months
after his detention, the news finally
arrives. Otto is
unconscious.
An extraction team of doctors and
diplomats is put together. And finally,
let
>> me start by saying that I'm glad
Secretary of State Rex Tillerson and I
along with a very talented team were
able to get Otto Warm back with his
parents.
>> Otto Warbeer is returned to US soil on
June 13. We're thrilled that our son is
on American soil and I'm able to talk to
you on Otto's behalf and I'm able to
wear the jacket that he wore when he
gave his confession. Otto, I love you
and I'm so crazy about you.
Last night being able to see Otto for
the first time in gosh, I bet it's 18
months. It was it was fantastic. Otto's
not in great shape right now and he's
been through a real tough time and it's
great to have him with us and [music]
I'm very proud of him.
>> Otto is home, but he's changed
tremendously.
When Cindy and Fred met Otto at the
airport, they were shocked.
>> We walked over to the plane. We heard
this howling, involuntary, [music]
inhuman sound. Otto was on the stretcher
across in the plane and he was jerking
violently making these inhuman sounds.
Otto had a shaved head. He had a feeding
tube coming out of his nose. He was
blind. He was deaf.
He was taken to the University of
Cincinnati Medical C Center's
neuroscience intensive care unit where
extensive imaging and diagnostic tests
immediately began.
>> His vital signs were stable upon arrival
and have remained so.
>> He doesn't need help breathing, no signs
of infection, no dysfunction of
non-neurological organs. His
neurological condition, though, is
described as unresponsive wakefulness.
what used to be called a vegetative
state. He blinks. Sometimes his eyes
open, but he isn't aware of his
surroundings and doesn't respond to
verbal commands. He doesn't speak.
Sometimes he moves, but his motions
aren't intentional. His arms and legs
are extremely weak.
>> Well, we thought he was in a coma, but
uh you couldn't call it a coma.
>> The warm beers remain at his bedside as
the tests are conducted. Our image of
Otto, as you know, was of someone just
wonderful,
beautiful inside and out. And to see how
he came home was too much for us. But,
uh, I almost passed out, but I got it
together and I rode in the ambulance
with him cuz I did not want him to be
alone anymore. He'd been alone for way
too long.
He's surrounded by his loved ones, but
his condition soon worsens. He develops
a high fever, 40° C.
Fred and Cindy Warbeer are told [music]
that he'll never wake up, and they ask
to have his feeding tube removed.
6 days after his release,
Otto is dead.
The news travels across the world.
>> The family of Otto Warbeer has said
goodbye. That's not
[music]
[music] the American student who fell
into a coma while in North Korean
custody and has died.
>> On June 22 in Wyoming, Ohio, more than
2,500 people attend his funeral. The
condition in which Otto Warbeer came
back to the US and his subsequent death
are discussed nationwide.
He left the United States in good
health. He returned [music] on the brink
of death.
>> Do you know what happened to him in
North Korea? I
I don't.
>> Content note. The following chapter
discusses suicide. Viewer discretion is
advised.
Upon his release, North Korea gave an
explanation for Otto's state. They said
he contracted bachulism, a rare and
severe kind of food poisoning, after
eating a meal of spinach and pork. After
he fell ill, they gave him a sleeping
pill to which he had some sort of
unexpected reaction which sent him into
a state of unresponsive wakefulness.
But US medical experts are quick to
dispute this story. Three doctors,
experts in neurology, ran tests on Otto
while he was still alive. At the request
of the family, they hold a press
conference to give their opinions.
>> Those tests did not reveal any evidence
of active or chronic denervation, nor
any uh repetitive stimulation that would
suggest active botulism at this time.
>> The North Koreans, it seems, are lying.
[music] And the Warbeers have a
different story.
>> They tortured him. They intentionally
injured him. It looked like someone had
taken a pair of pliers and rearranged
his bottom teeth. He had a large scar on
his right foot.
>> They destroyed him.
>> They They purposely and [music]
intentionally
injured Otto.
>> On September 25, 2017, Fred and Cindy
Warbeer gave an interview on Fox and
Friends. Trump apparently watched. This
becomes the narrative. Physical torture.
and as a consequence brain damage. But
soon serious doubts emerge.
Let's go through his injuries one by
one. First there was a noticeable scar
on Otto's right foot. This is Dr.
Lakshmi Kota Samarco. The coroner
selected to conduct an external autopsy.
Fred Warbeer had noticed the scar. But
had Dr. Samarco
>> physically as far as wounds [music]
there were a few small scars that we
documented. There was one that we really
couldn't explain for medical
instrumentation, which some of the other
scars we could, but there wasn't
anything on the external examination to
indicate um other than that one scar
that we couldn't explain to indicate
torture.
>> The Warbeers opted against a complete
autopsy, offering no reason for this
decision. But Dr. Samarco did perform an
external inspection. Later, in a lawsuit
against North Korea, [music] an expert
witness cited the scar on Otto's foot as
potential evidence that he was subjected
to torture, possibly electric shock. But
does this injury prove Otto was
tortured? No. Then there are his teeth.
Fred Warbeer said it looked as though
Otto's bottom teeth had been rearranged.
Dr. Samarco couldn't confirm this.
>> We also consulted our forensic dentist,
Dr. right? And I had him take a look at
the imaging specifically dealing with
the lower teeth and mandible. He agreed
with us that there is no evidence of
trauma to the lower teeth or man.
>> In the lawsuit, this finding was
disputed. Two of Otto's private dentists
testified that his post-mortem dental
X-rays, when compared to previous
X-rays, indicated that some of his lower
teeth had been bent backward, movement
consistent with an impact injury. The
New York Times had reported that Otto
had been repeatedly beaten. That's not
impossible. An ex-N North Korean spy who
was familiar with, though not directly
involved in Otto's case, said he'd heard
Otto was roughed up by prison guards.
[music]
He also continues to say that there
might have been water boarding. To him,
that's standard practice, what he'd call
battery rather than torture. It's
difficult to say whether this ex spy is
credible, though. And even if Otto's
teeth were bent backward, it's
impossible to know for certain what
caused that. Finally, the biggest injury
of all, his brain injury.
>> The most important diagnostic test thus
far was a magnetic resonance imaging
scan of the brain. This study showed
extensive loss of brain tissue in all
regions of the brain.
>> In other words, the damage is universal
and scans show it occurred all at once.
There's a technical term for this, an
[music] enoxic encphylopathy. It means
an injury caused by a lack of oxygen to
the brain. So, either blood ceased to
flow to Otto's brain, which would result
in a lack of oxygen, or Otto stopped
breathing. This pattern of brain injury,
however, is usually seen as a result of
cardopulmonary arrest where the blood
supply to the brain is inadequate for a
period of time resulting in the death of
brain tissue.
>> In general terms, one of the more likely
causes of a cardiopulmonary arrest in a
young person would have been a
respiratory arrest.
>> In all likelihood, Otto stopped
breathing. Any number of events could
have caused this. an allergic reaction,
choking, near drowning, anything that
might prevent oxygen from reaching his
brain. But which of these events was the
cause? There's no way to know.
We have no certain or verifiable
knowledge of the cause or circumstances
of his neurological injury.
>> A cause that could almost certainly be
ruled out was repeated beatings.
Repeated beings to the head would have
caused asymmetrical damage with some
regions being affected more than others.
Also, scans revealed no fractures of the
skull. Despite all this uncertainty, the
warmbeers insist on torture.
And the question of whether Otto was
tortured or not is not a medical side
note. By now, it has the potential to
escalate a simmering conflict between
two nuclear powers.
A year and a half before, mere days
after Otto's detention, North Korea had
carried out its fourth nuclear test in
defiance of international sanctions. It
also launched a longrange missile. In
September 2016, it performed another
nuclear test. By 2017, the year of
return, the confrontation between the US
and North Korea was near the boiling
point. North Korea best not make any
more threats to the United States.
They will be met with fire and fury
like the world has never seen. It was
the beginning of the 2017 2018 North
Korea crisis. Meanwhile, Otto Warbeer's
case took on increased political weight.
Trump had adopted the torture hypothesis
as fact. Senator John McCain said Otto
had been tortured and murdered. Senators
Adam Schiff and Marco Rubio also used
the word murder. Fred Warbeer's analysis
was that his son served as a sort of
human shield. North Korea doesn't do
anything by mistake. It was their fourth
nuclear weapons test and they had a lot
of things they wanted to cover and they
felt like Otto was going to provide them
the security they needed to get away
with these things.
Then in 2018, Michael Flukinger, the
doctor that helped bring Otto back to
the US, revealed a new piece of
information to GQ. The staff at the
North Korean hospital where Otto stayed,
told Flukinger that they received him
the day after his trial, and he was
already unresponsive. They had to
resuscitate him, then give him oxygen
and put him on a ventilator, or he would
die, Flukinger told GQ. Also, there's a
brain scan dated April 2016.
>> We received copies of brain MRI images
from the medical personnel in North
Korea. The earliest images are dated
April 2016. Based upon our analysis of
those images, the brain injury likely
occurred in the preceding weeks.
>> Of course, the North Korean story might
be a lie. It might not be true that he
was hospitalized the morning after his
trial, but there is strong medical
evidence that he sustained his brain
injury in the days or weeks after March
16.
In any case, Otto Warbeer was sentenced
to 15 years of hard labor, but it's very
unlikely that he was actually sent to
one of the notoriously horrific North
Korean labor camps. [music]
American detainees are treated
differently. According to GQ, Otto
Wararmbeer most likely stayed in a used
guest house in downtown Pyongyang during
his detention. The hard labor he was
sentenced to [music] would likely have
been planting soybeans and making
bricks. Grueling, backbreaking work, but
nothing compared to coal mining, which
is typical for North Koreans. North
Korea needed him as a bargaining chip.
And bargaining chips don't have much
value if they aren't in good condition.
And in a sense he was
>> we believe that for somebody who's been
bedridden for more than a year that his
body was in excellent condition. His
skin was in excellent condition and we
didn't see any evidence of decubit eye
or bed sores.
>> In its article GQ proposes a different
theory than torture. During the two
months between his detention and his
confession, Otto was likely subjected to
relentless interrogation for as long as
15 hours per day. The only respit from
the interrogation would have been North
Korean propaganda films. Previous
prisoners were told their government had
forgotten them. Some fell into
debilitating depressions, even
attempting suicide. at trial. So, hours,
weeks, or days before he supposedly fell
into a coma, he was visibly desperate.
>> Please think of my family.
>> Give me the oldest son in my family.
>> GQ speculates that in the hopeless hours
after his sentencing, Otto may have
attempted to take his own life. The lack
of oxygen to his brain could have caused
his injury. Of course, this theory is
just one of many. An allergic reaction
to a sleeping pill, an excessive
administration of drugs, a suicide
attempt, a heart attack, a form of
torture that left no obvious lasting
marks. It could have been any of these
things. Without Otto here to tell the
tale, we may never know the truth.
[music]
In May 2018, something weird happened.
Trump tweeted that he was going to meet
Kim Jong-un in person and everything
changed.
>> Getting a good picture, everybody. So,
he look nice and handsome and thin.
>> After the Singapore summit, Otto's name
all but disappeared from Trump's lips,
replaced by the name of Kim Jong-un.
>> And then we fell in love. Okay. No,
really. He wrote me beautiful letters,
and they're great letters. We fell in
love. [snorts] The previous year, Trump
tweeted that he tried so hard to be
Kim's friend and referred to their
relationship as
>> it's a very special relationship.
>> In 2019, when asked whether he thought
Kim knew about Otto's case, his reply
was startling.
>> I don't believe he knew about it.
>> The Warbeers were outraged. Trump had
helped them bring Otto home and relisted
Kim Jong-un's country as a state sponsor
of terrorism. Now he seems to admire
him.
>> Well, he is very talented. Anybody that
takes over a situation like he did at 26
years of age and is able to run it and
run it tough. Very few people at that
age you can take one out of 10,000
probably couldn't do it.
>> Otto Warmbeer [music]
was many things. An all-American boy, an
unlucky tourist, a loving son. But on
the international stage, he was a pawn
and a symbol. Pyongyang deployed Otto on
the chessboard of politics, using him
domestically as a mouthpiece to spread
anti-American propaganda and
internationally as a bargaining chip, a
hostage to be traded for the easing of
sanctions or other US concessions. For
the Trump administration, Otto Warbeer
was useful as a symbol, driving the
narrative that he was tortured by a
barbarous regime and possibly using his
death as a means of psychologically
preparing the American public for war.
The threat of which Trump hoped would
make Kim back down.
Otto was sentenced to 15 years hard
labor for an alleged crime that in most
countries would be considered at worst
vandalism based on a sham trial. No
matter what happened to him, that in
itself is damning enough. And even if he
likely never had to go to one of North
Korea's prison camps, they are hell on
earth. Uncertainty about his cause of
death shouldn't distract from the
exceptional brutality and cruelty of Kim
Jong-un's regime.